A Guide to the Papers of Francis Scott Key, 1808-1841
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Francis Scott Key 1808-1841
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6949
24 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was acquired through deposit, gift, and purchase from 1962-1991.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 24 items, chiefly correspondence of Francis Scott Key.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into two series. Series I consists of letters and Series II consists of miscellany.
Contents List
- Series I: Letters
  - Francis Scott Key to Mrs. Maria West 1808 Mar 6, ALS, 2p.
    Key asks Mrs. West to use her influence and example on his wife Polly to think seriously about the important things of life, from Francis Scott Key Polly might think this preaching or scolding and hopes Maria West can be more persuasive.
  - Francis Scott Key to Mrs. Murdock 1810 Aug 22, ALS, 3p.
    Key writes to his Aunt Murdock at the request of Dr. Shaaff to inform her of the condition of Dr. Shaff's wife, she suffers from a disordered mind after her confinement, and also has a dread of death, condemnation and refuses all comfort.
  - Francis Scott Key to Mrs. Ann Phoebe Key 1811 Jul 16, ALS, 2p.
    Key writes that Milley and her husband are coming to spend time at Pipe Creek and hopes a stay with her will improve Milley's health.
  - Francis Scott Key to Mrs. Ann Phoebe Key 1813 Apr 21, ALS, 4p.
    Key discusses the possibility of Mr. Landers starting a school at Taney Town or Emmitsburg, writes about the placement of two girls and a boy as apprentices in Georgetown, bird drawing at bottom of page 3.
  - Francis Scott Key to Mrs. Ann Phoebe Key 1813 Jul 5, ALS, 2p.
    Key discusses the proposed school with Mr. Landers as the teacher.
  - Francis Scott Key to Mrs. Ann Phoebe Key 1813 Dec 27, ALS, 2p.
    Key discusses health of Aunt Scott and Uncle Scott of Annapolis, mentions duel in Washington between Grosvenor and Calhoun and will speak in Alexandria on General Washington's birthday.
  - Francis Scott Key to Mrs. Ann Phoebe Key 1814 Jan 2, ALS, 1p.
    Key states that he is busy at court but would like to get to Pipe Creek to see his mother and father, has had erysipelas on hands and wears gloves, living expenses in Georgetown are high and the war does not seem to be going well.
  - Francis Scott Key to Mrs. Ann Phoebe Key 1814 Dec 4, ALS, 3p.
    Key discusses the need for a newspaper to introduce to the public a better set of principles in politics to save the country from being torn to pieces by factions.
  - Francis Scott Key to Mrs. Ann Phoebe Key 1815 May 4, ALS, 2p.
    His wife, Polly, has been sick but is now recovering, discusses some people who are ill and the need for faith in God during such times.
  - Francis Scott Key to Mrs. Ann Phoebe Key 1816 Jan 20, ALS, 2p.
    Key discusses illness in his family and Dr. Shaaf's family, primarily measles, mentions his heavy workload and the Yazoo business which is so troublesome and has interfered with other concerns.
  - Francis Scott Key to Mrs. Ann Phoebe Key 1816 Jun 22, ALS, 3p.
    Reports the birth of a fine boy, Daniel Murray, to Polly, mentions Mrs. Landers's good fortune, and old soldier when drinking came to their home when he was away and scared Polly.
  - Francis Scott Key to Mrs. Ann Phoebe Key 1817 Nov 24, ALS, 2p.
    Key mentions sending agents to Africa and will get a report concerning colonization, comments on the education and training of girls and bys, requests that his father send timothy and buckwheat seed.
  - Francis Scott Key to Mrs. Ann Phoebe Key 1819 May 21, ALS, 2p.
    Key is disappointed in not having been able to get up to see her, his wife, Polly, had a fever but is now recovered, Mr. Munro died but his conversations before death affected a great number of people who visited him.
  - Francis Scott Key to Mrs. Ann Phoebe Key 1819 Oct 5, ALS, 2p.
    Key mentions family matters and has not sold boys' horses yet, plan of having a colonization society meeting in New York is given up because of yellow fever there.
  - Francis Scott Key to Mrs. Ann Phoebe Key 1822 May 4, ALS, 1p.
    Key writes that since he did not receive letter he is worried, sends his love to his sister, Anne Arnold Key [Mrs. Roger Brooke Taney], and her children, Mrs. West and her family are with Keys.
  - Francis Scott Key to Lewis Cass 1834 Apr 11, ALS, 1p.
    At the request of Mr. Taney, writes to inform Lewis Cass that the Farmers and Mechanics Bank of Georgetown is in perilous condition and any government funds there should be secured.
  - Francis Scott Key to Bedford Brown 1837 Aug 26, ALS, 1p.
    Key recommends Mr. Middleton for a vacant position.
  - Francis Scott Key to Charles Key 1840 Feb 2, ALS, 4p.
    Key writes to his son and tells him the family news about the dog, Bruin, at the end includes long poem, "The Well of St. Keyne."
  - Francis Scott Key to Charles Key 1840 Feb 5, ALS, 2p.
    Key writes to his son at Elkridge and tells him not to worry about his school paper or money, the shoemaker will trust him until Francis Scott Key comes or sends money, other news about family.
  - Francis Scott Key to Mary Tayloe Lloyd Key 1841 Apr 26, ALS, 1p.
    Key writes from St. Louis on his way to Fort Madison, St. Louis appears to be a splendid city and he hopes to stop a day or so on the way back, many logs and trees in river.
  - Francis Scott Key to Charles Key 1841 Jun 19, ALS, 3p.
    Key will go to Pipe Creek to get house ready for family to go there for summer, Mr. Fendall nominated as District Attorney in his place, other family news.
  - Francis Scott Key to Charles Key 1841 Sep 11, ALS, 1p.
    Key discusses son's school plans for next winter and family news from Pipe Creek, Alice writes they miss the boys and beaux and hopes some cousins and friends will come to visit, on same sheet: letter from Alice Key to her brother Charles.
  - Francis Scott Key to D. Middleton n.d., ALS, 1p.
    Key writes that he is enclosing notes.
- Series II: Miscellaneous
  - List of legal papers 1814 Dec 12, ADS, 3p.
    List of papers and documents in the possession of Francis Scott Key respecting the Yazoo claim.